In June 1944, the Allies landed in
Normandy. It would take them nearly 100
days to break German resistance.
100 days of glory in a vast operation
unequaled in history.
100 days of living hell for soldiers on
both sides.
Civilian men, women, and children were
violently thrown into the chaos.
100 days during which the outcome of the
battle hung in the balance several
times.
100 days of honor and horror.
>> [music]
>> Through the stories of the men and
women, civilians and soldiers, Germans
and Allies who lived through it, we can
relive the story [music] of these 100
days during which the whole world held
its breath.
In 1944, the Nazi regime had held the
old continent in its iron grip for four
long years.
>> [music]
>> France, the Netherlands, Belgium,
Luxembourg, Denmark, Czechoslovakia, and
Norway were all occupied.
If they were to eradicate the brown
plague, the allies had to land. [music]
Caught between the Soviet hammer to the
east and the Anglo-American anvil to the
west, the Third Reich would eventually
capitulate.
Hitler and his officers were aware of
the threat, but they were convinced
[music] they would triumph.
The Führer boasted,
>> "The plutocratic Western world [music]
can attempt its landing whenever it
desires. It will fail."
>> And with good reason. Germany had spent
months preparing for its enemy by
building its Atlantic Wall.
Stretching 4,000 km from Norway to
Spain, this new Great Wall of China
required 13 [music] million tons of
concrete.
It was defended by almost a million
soldiers.
Cannon traps and bunkers protected the
beaches.
An unbreachable barrier.
Its construction was overseen by the
legendary Field Marshal Rommel.
The question on every German soldier's
lips was, "When would the landing take
place?"
19-year-old Franz Gockel was stationed
with his unit on the Normandy beaches.
>> Every day since January, all the talk
has been about the invasion.
Would the Americans and British land
here or not?
Obviously not, most people said.
And others insisted within [music] the
next 4 weeks.
I couldn't even look at the sea without
thinking about them landing.
>> The wait was nerve-racking. Marshall
Rommel made sure he kept his troops
motivated.
But privately, Rommel confided
>> The most decisive battle of the war and
the fate of the German people are at
stake.
The landing will take place here in
Normandy.
And it will be the longest day.
>> Rommel was right.
For 6 months, a vast machine had been
preparing for the operation [music] that
was to liberate Europe.
More than 3 million soldiers assembled
in England.
1,700,000 of them British, 1 and 1/2
million Americans, 200,000 Canadians,
Australians, and New Zealanders along
with French, Polish, Belgian troops
among many others.
The Allies had built up a colossal
arsenal.
England had become the greatest military
base in history.
As a youngster, John Keegan lived south
of London.
>> That spring, it wasn't wheat growing in
the fields, but ammunitions.
Thousands of acres of mortars,
howitzers, and anti-aircraft guns.
The south of England had become a vast
transit camp.
>> Every British town was full of tourists
in uniform who found accommodation
however they could.
But space was short and thinking outside
the box was vital.
For weeks, soldiers of all nationalities
trained in Britain.
In all weathers
and in real conditions.
Sometimes these training drills could
take a turn for the worse.
In April 1944, a landing drill was
taking place on an English beach.
Suddenly, there was a surprise attack by
German torpedo boats.
The raid cost over 600 lives.
A dreadful setback taking place just 6
weeks before D-Day.
The terrible news was kept secret to
avoid discouraging the troops.
>> The 130,000 men who were to land on
D-Day were gripped by anxiety.
But they did their best to keep fear at
bay.
Frenchman Leon Gautier joined Kieffer's
Commandos, the only French unit to land
on the first day.
>> The days leading up to the landing are
very calm.
We also [music] have time to unwind.
One of our games is making a trampoline
out of the canvas [music] tarpaulin and
using it to throw a man up into the air.
He has to try to catch a hold of the
bench forming to the bottom.
>> Even the officers were not immune to the
tension.
While the American General Eisenhower
and his staff publicly displayed their
confidence in front of the cameras, they
[music] were worried that the operation
would fail.
They carried the crushing responsibility
for the world's destiny on their
shoulders.
They were already [music] pointing at
Berlin on the map, but the road was
still long.
They planned one of the riskiest
operations of all time, code-named
Overlord.
On the 5th of June, 1944, at dawn,
almost 7,000 ships were to set sail from
the coast of England. Having braved
nearly 200 km of the English Channel,
the Allied soldiers would land on five
Normandy beaches.
The Americans on two beaches nicknamed
Utah and Omaha.
The British and Canadians on three
beaches, Gold, Juno, and Sword.
The slightest leak of information could
scupper the entire operation. The
generals [music] were becoming
increasingly paranoid, and for good
reason. Emotions had been running high
for a number of weeks.
Several clues in the Daily Telegraph's
crossword hinted at the operations code
names.
Overlord, Omaha, and Sword.
Was it coincidence or inside knowledge
of a secret agent?
Worse still, in April [music] 1944,
General Henry Miller, who was drunk at
the time, let slip that [music] the
landing was to take place in early June.
He was immediately demoted and sent back
to the USA.
British Prime Minister Winston Churchill
thundered,
"In wartime, truth is so precious that
she should always be attended by a
bodyguard of lies."
This bodyguard of lies was called
Fortitude. It was a vast program of
disinformation.
A Spanish double agent known as Garbo,
from his real name Juan Pujol Garcia,
was in contact with the German
leadership. He spoon-fed them fanciful
reports.
To make the illusion more convincing,
fake units were created made out of
rubber.
Formations of inflatable tanks and
imitation aircraft were put in position
near Dover.
The objective was to convince the
Germans that the landing would take
place near Calais,
the part of the French coast closest to
England.
On the 3rd of June, the troops boarded
ship.
While waiting to kill Germans, they
killed time.
The soldiers played cards, [music]
wrote, or listened to the officers'
briefings, hoping they would survive.
While some prayed they would go to
heaven, others knew they [music] were
bound straight for hell.
On the morning of the 4th of June, the
massive armada set sail.
The soldiers finally knew their
destination. They'd been given a tourist
brochure for France.
Englishman Ron Smith had just embarked.
>> I was scared.
Someone said, "France, we can't go
there." And the commander said,
"Not only can you go there, but you will
go, and you won't need a passport."
>> Leon Gauthier said,
>> The information soon reached the French
group.
We're going to land at home, in
Normandy. We can finally return to
France. The news raised our spirits.
>> Soon after they left, the weather
forecast turned ugly.
A storm threatened the success of the
operation.
The first convoys heading for the French
coast were called back urgently.
Lloyd Brantley was a radio operator on
the way to Normandy.
>> There had been radio silence for hours.
Then suddenly three digits flashed on my
terminal.
It was incredible. The landing had been
put back.
The 865 strong fleet had to turn around
and return to England.
>> The top brass panicked. Had all the
ships received the message?
To prevent a disaster, a seaplane took
off urgently to alert the 139 ships that
had not responded.
On the 5th of June, 1944, trapped aboard
their boats, the men watched for the
desperately awaited signal.
When suddenly the chief meteorologist
noticed that a lull in the storm was due
at dawn the next day.
This provided a very slim chance for a
successful launch of Operation Overlord.
Commander-in-Chief Dwight Eisenhower
went for broke, uttering the fateful
words, "Let's go."
On the evening of the 5th of June, he
inspected [music] several units to
support and encourage them.
Something soldier Samuel Fuller never
forgot.
>> Eisenhower [music] walked among us and
spoke to us in his calm and reassuring
voice.
We listened to him
and took strength [music] from his words
about our departure on a great crusade.
He told us
the eyes of the world are upon you.
>> I went to [music] visit the parachute
units who would be the first to jump
over France.
The soldiers reassured him. One of them
even promised him a job on his Texas
[music] ranch after the war.
People were joking to hide the stress.
Eisenhower's driver, Kay Summersby, said
>> As we went back to the [music] car, he
told me, "It's very hard to look a
soldier in the eye when you fear you're
sending [music] him to his death."
And I saw tears in his eyes.
>> Thousands of airborne troops were
getting ready.
Parachutist Ashton Landry said
>> I carry over 100 cartridges, a big
pistol strapped to my leg, a pack of
explosives to the other.
Along with my parachute and my life
belt,
my normal body weight goes from 65 kilos
to 120 kilos.
>> David Webster recalled,
"The whole ground shook with the noise
of the engines.
My legs turned to cotton wool. My throat
was tight. I could only speak in a
whisper."
Thousands of paras were dropped behind
enemy lines to seize control of the
bridges and secure the area behind the
beaches.
The paras were accompanied by hundreds
of gliders.
A total of 20,000 men and several dozen
tons of equipment were transported
through the air.
Nearly 7,000 warships sailed for the
French coast once more. The greatest
armada ever assembled.
>> [music]
>> Canadian soldier Charles Fox [music]
said,
"The channel was covered in ships.
You could have almost crossed it on foot
by going from one ship to another."
German soldier Franz Gockel was keeping
watch from his post on a Normandy beach.
>> A sentry came at midnight to relieve me.
I hope they're not going to bother us
with another one of those stupid alert
drills tonight.
I said to the radio guys.
And then I disappeared underground,
threw my boots down, and jumped into my
bunk fully clothed.
>> On the ships, the men were shaking.
They made their way to their landing
barges.
Tossed about by the sea and full of the
copious breakfast they'd been given, the
soldiers were as sick as dogs.
Samuel Fuller
>> The waves crashed against the barges and
washed the vomit that was spread across
the decks.
All that vomit made us feel like we were
wearing ice skates rather than boots.
>> Leon Gautier
>> There were just under a hundred men in
our barge, all very calm and
concentrated.
Commander Kieffer told us, "Fewer than
10 of us will make it back in one
piece."
We all hoped we'd be one of this 10.
>> [music]
>> Jess Weiss
>> I was so frightened.
We were going to die.
In a few minutes or maybe in an hour.
Dead forever.
It was all any of us could think about.
We were even thinking if I could only
get a million-dollar injury.
Meaning [music] losing a leg, an arm.
Anything that would get me sent home.
But there was nothing we could do.
Nowhere to run.
We were bound for death.
>> [bell]
>> Franz Gockel in his bunker was rudely
awakened from his slumber.
>> An officer yelled through the door.
This really is it this time, boys.
They're coming.
It was dramatic. We pulled our boots on,
grabbed our rifles, and ran to our
positions by the machine guns and the
mortars.
>> Heinrich Severloh, a 20-year-old German,
was astounded by what he was witnessing.
[music]
The landing fleet was like a great city.
The huge Anglo-American armada was there
in front of us. It was going to be a
hell of a fight.
>> As the barges approached, the allies
launched a gigantic aerial bombardment
to break the Atlantic wall and delay the
arrival of reinforcements.
>> Then the Navy took over, their cannon
pounding the beaches.
A GI on one of the barges said to his
friend,
>> Look at what they're dishing out to the
Germans.
I bet there won't be one man left
standing.
>> Franz Gockel was at his post.
>> The earth shook. The beach became a
volcano.
I was caught in a cloud of smoke and
sulfur.
My eyes and nose full of dust.
I prayed. I prayed out loud.
>> Not far away, even the people of
Normandy were subjected to this rain of
fire and took refuge in cellars or
improvised shelters.
Angel Marie Degaye lived in the Calvados
region.
>> There were 10 of us in a trench designed
for four. It was all very cramped. I
didn't feel safe.
Some of us started saying our rosaries.
The shells whistled over our heads.
Lots of them fell all around.
I thought we were going to get buried
alive.
>> The soldiers on the barges were also
saying their prayers.
Just before the onslaught, one soldier
pleaded with his God.
>> My Lord, I'm soon to be very
preoccupied. I will probably forget you,
but please don't forget me.
>> On Omaha Beach, the Atlantic Wall stood
firm.
The Germans had their orders.
They were to wait until the Allied
soldiers broke cover. Then, they would
open fire.
Franz Gockel.
>> The slaughter had begun.
We shot at anything that moved. Soon the
beach was covered with the bodies of
American soldiers.
I must have shot over 400 bursts.
>> The photographer, Robert Capa, known
throughout the world for his photographs
of the Spanish Civil War, landed with
the GIs.
He too started shooting.
>> I didn't dare to take my eyes off the
finder of my contacts and frantically
shot frame after frame.
The men around me lay motionless. Only
the dead on the waterline rolled with
the waves.
I just stayed behind my tank repeating a
little sentence from my Spanish Civil
War days.
Es una cosa muy seria.
This is a very serious business.
>> These photos taken in the heat of action
bear witness [music] to the soldiers
distress.
The men were trapped.
It was impossible for them to advance
through the hail of bullets around them.
>> [music]
>> Jess Weiss
There were no trees, nor bushes, nor
sand dunes to provide any kind of cover.
None of the shell craters that the
Allied Air Force was supposed to have
caused with the morning bombing raid.
I threw myself to the ground
instinctively.
Seeking the meager protection that the
bodies of my dead comrades could offer.
And I stayed there for a moment,
petrified, with my head resting against
a corpse.
The soldiers on the other American
beach, Utah, east of the village of
Sainte-Mère-Église, were more fortunate.
The Germans offered only meager
resistance there.
Some were even buried alive in the
barrage.
On Sword Beach, near Ouistreham, the
French commandos led by Kieffer landed.
Léon Gautier was in the lead barge.
I jumped in the water with the lads from
the troop and headed for the beach.
We were the first to put our feet on the
sand.
That was it. Here we were.
This was our land of France that we had
left some years ago, and now we were
back.
She seemed to be trembling under the
cannon fire and the machine gun bursts.
>> Further east, the British had thought of
everything. Bagpiper Bill Millin took
charge of galvanizing the men.
>> The sound rang out through the chaos on
the beach.
Someone yelled out that this was a fine
time to play music.
But other lads flashed me a victory
sign.
>> On Juno and Gold beaches, the English
and Canadians were making progress.
Canadian Alfred Turnbull recalled,
>> "I could see assault craft exploding on
the beach, and the bodies of the crews
torn to shreds.
Despite these horrors,
the army landed."
>> While the British troops were pushing
inland, on Omaha Beach, the soldiers
were still enduring a living hell,
despite the reinforcements. The Germans
were still in control of the situation.
Heinrich Severloh
>> "I was shooting at anything that moved
in the water and on the beach.
They brought me at least 8,000 bullets.
It was like lambs to the slaughter."
>> There was no way out for the wounded.
If they retreated, they would drown. If
they advanced,
>> [music]
>> they would be shot.
Many of them drowned before the fighting
was over.
Samuel Fuller
>> "We started to see bloodied bodies
floating around us.
Some were still alive, pleading with us
to help them.
It was awful.
We fought like men possessed to avoid
drowning.
>> The situation was so desperate that the
high command even considered leaving
Omaha Beach to its fate and sacrificing
the men who had already landed.
Paradoxically, [music]
the horrendous weather had worked in the
allies' favor.
The German top brass had let their guard
down and not all of them were in
Normandy. Rommel was in Germany
celebrating his wife's birthday.
General Marks of the 84th Corps was
happily drinking at his 53rd birthday
party with his chiefs of staff.
The only tank division in Normandy was
led by General Edgar Feuchtinger.
But, he was in Paris in the arms of his
mistress.
After several hours of fighting, the
allies gained the upper hand.
But, the German high command still
believed that the landing was nothing
more than a diversion.
Hitler was not woken up until 10:00 in
the morning. He stuck to his guns. The
invasion would happen in the
Pas-de-Calais.
Operation Fortitude had been a success.
It was not until 2:30 p.m. that the
Führer agreed to send reinforcements.
He said,
>> "The beach should be cleared by tonight
at the latest."
>> The Allied position remained highly
precarious.
If large numbers of German divisions
arrived, they could be driven back into
the sea.
However, the Allies had an asset.
The French Resistance sprang into
action.
They'd been waiting for their moment for
a long time.
Resistance fighter André Heureaux-Cécil
recalled,
>> "I rushed off. I left my wife and my
2-month-old son. No one could have
stopped me that night.
I was burning to fight and kick the
invader out, like my father had done in
World War I."
>> Despite its slender resources, the
Shadow Army carried out thousands of
acts of sabotage to slow the arrival of
German reinforcements to the French
coastline.
On the evening of the longest day,
General Eisenhower's men held the
beaches.
10,000 Allied soldiers were dead,
wounded, or missing.
It was the same for the Germans.
The Allied top brass had been expecting
far worse losses.
But, the situation remained precarious.
The day was not yet won.
Of course, German news did everything to
reassure its viewers.
In spite of these lies, news of the
landing spread like a powder trail
thanks to the BBC, which many French
people listened to in secret.
Benoît Gru was a young student in Paris.
>> Four years of occupation, of secret
messages, clandestine [music]
radio, the hopes of millions of French
people have led to the only news we were
waiting for, the landings. [music]
The official German communication said,
"The Anglo-Americans landed in Normandy
last night and were repelled almost
everywhere."
It was that word, almost, that allowed
us to hope.
>> Several small villages fell into Allied
hands.
But the Germans did not drop their
guard. Their troops fought fiercely.
In this merciless fight, no quarter was
given by either camp.
The Allies sometimes killed their
prisoners.
Frenchwoman Huguette Verdier said,
>> "The Englishmen told us that there were
no prison camps, so they had to be shot.
He took the three Germans away.
I don't know what happened to them, but
for me, all I can remember is the young
soldier's pale face and trembling body."
>> The Germans were renowned for their
cruelty, none more so than the Hitler
Youth wing of the 12th SS division.
Radicalized from childhood, they
committed ever more atrocities to prove
to their elders that they were worthy of
Hitler's trust.
Their division captured dozens of
Canadian soldiers.
These men, who were about to die, were
filmed for the last time.
One of them, George Meakin,
>> [music]
>> wrote to his mother.
>> "This may be my last chance to write to
you before the big day.
If you don't hear from me for a long
time, don't worry. Just keep smiling,
and everything will be fine."
>> [music]
>> He was murdered in the courtyard of
Audrieu Castle east of Caen along with
44 other Canadian soldiers.
His body was found after the war with
the remains of dozens of Allied soldiers
in gruesome mass graves.
Concerned about an attack from the rear,
the Wehrmacht exterminated any pockets
of resistance it encountered without
mercy.
Resistance fighters, usually poorly
armed volunteers, were liquidated
wherever they were.
Even the civilian population was not
spared.
On the 10th of June 1944 in
Oradour-sur-Glane,
643 citizens were shot or burned alive
in the village church.
Marcel Dartout was 20 years old.
>> There were four or five of us, and guess
what we were talking about.
Football and our game the next day.
Then the Germans arrived.
Suddenly, the first shots rang out.
I took two bullets to my lower leg and I
fell.
It was my friends [music] who saved me.
They all had fallen on top of me.
>> These acts of retribution took place in
many other villages.
On the 12th of June 1944, the Allies
finally occupied an 80 km long United
bridgehead.
The battle for Normandy had begun.
The strategy was simple. The English and
Canadians had to take the city of Caen,
an essential communications [music]
hub.
A mere formality, according to the
English General Montgomery, who reckoned
on seizing it in a few days.
The Americans' objective, meanwhile, was
Cherbourg, a deepwater port vital for
landing troops and equipment.
It became a race between the Allies and
the Germans. Whichever camp managed to
get the greatest number of soldiers to
Normandy would be victorious.
To help them win the battle, the Allies
brought two artificial harbors along
with them.
The code name, Mulberry.
It was the world's greatest Lego set,
made up of huge keys, platforms, and
7,000-ton concrete cases.
Quick to assemble, they allowed 2,000 to
3,000 tons of equipment to be
transported per day.
Eager to witness the theater of
operations, British Prime Minister
Winston Churchill went to Normandy and
congratulated his favorite general,
Montgomery.
Churchill savored the moment.
For four long years, Great Britain had
been resisting Hitler's armies.
The 12th of June gave the old warhorse
a taste of revenge.
But aside from the living, there
remained thousands of dead.
A makeshift cemetery stood on a stretch
of a beach.
Samuel Fuller
>> Of the 183 men in my company who landed,
about 100 were dead, wounded, or
reported missing.
There's no such thing as a hero.
All that can save a guy is experience
[music]
and intuition.
But most of all, luck.
>> These men knew they had survived thanks
to the first waves of attackers who had
been mowed down.
They bowed their heads in honor of their
lost brothers in arms.
Churchill came to the Normandy beaches
followed by de Gaulle two days later.
The general had been waiting for this
moment since 1940.
He rallied around him the French who
wanted to carry on the fight.
Churchill and Roosevelt took care to
keep him away from the D-Day
preparations.
They refused to recognize his
legitimacy. De Gaulle had never been
elected.
On the 14th of June, the rebel played a
trump card.
when he went to the small town of
Bayeux.
General de Gaulle had left France four
long years previously.
Some French people knew his voice, but
the majority had no idea what he looked
like.
Claude Gascoigne, 10 years old.
>> I was curious, so I went up close to
[music] the soldiers. There was a tall
man, very striking.
I decided to walk alongside him.
It wasn't until later that I realized it
was de Gaulle.
I thought General de Gaulle was the king
of England.
>> de Gaulle gave a speech to a rapturous
crowd.
He created an embryonic administration
in this little corner of free France,
nominating [music] prefects and
deputies.
This demonstration of popularity worked
in his favor in the eyes of London and
Washington.
But the allies now had bigger fish to
fry.
In recent days, a revolutionary weapon
had appeared in the skies.
Germany's V1 flying bombs took off from
the French coast and rained down on
London.
The British thought they had seen the
last of the Blitz, but to their horror,
the nightmare had begun once more.
Young Londoner Betty Hedges recalled,
>> "The flying bombs are awful. You can see
them coming, and you hear them up in the
sky, [music]
and you just pray that the sound will
not stop.
But all of a sudden, it does stop, And
then the bomb falls. And then, you just
pray that it doesn't fall near you.
>> The Germans were convinced that these
miracle weapons would bring them
victory.
A young German wrote,
>> "We only talked about rockets. Maybe we
could fire some at America.
I am sure that we will be triumphant."
>> But some German generals were more
skeptical.
Hitler went to France to try to talk
them round.
His strategists demanded that the V1
missiles be deployed on the Normandy
front against [music] British ports or
American warships.
But Hitler was adamant.
>> "London. London. The V1 offensive will
convince the British to broker a peace.
Panic will destroy England."
>> Rommel stated that the struggle was now
futile. The Führer cut him off.
>> "Don't concern yourself with the outcome
of the war, but with your invasion
front."
>> Hitler made his way back to Germany.
Four years before his army had invaded
Paris.
But those victorious days were a thing
of the past. He was never to return to
France.
In June 1944, the Allies landed in
Normandy. It would take them nearly 100
days to break German resistance.
100 days of glory in a vast operation
unequaled in history.
100 days of living hell for soldiers on
both sides.
Civilian men, women, and children were
violently thrown into the chaos.
For 100 days, during which the outcome
of the battle hung in the balance
several times.
100 days of honor and horror.
Through the stories of the men and
women, civilians and soldiers, Germans
and allies who lived through it, we can
relive the story [music] of these 100
days, during which the whole world held
its breath.
On the 6th of June, 1944, the allies
landed on five French beaches in
Normandy.
After a terrible battle, they broke
through the Atlantic wall and took the
beaches.
10,000 soldiers were killed, wounded, or
disappeared.
Despite these losses, in just a few
days, the allies occupied a single
beachhead 50 miles long.
But their position was vulnerable to any
German counterattack.
If Hitler's divisions arrived in large
numbers, the allies could be thrown back
into the sea.
Thanks to two artificial harbors known
as Mulberries, the British and Americans
landed up to 3,000 tons of material a
day.
The Battle of the Beaches was over.
The Allies now had to advance inland,
but the Normandy campaign was to become
a nightmare.
The Anglo-American offensive got bogged
down. Hitler was helped by an unforeseen
advantage, the weather.
Between the 19th and the 22nd of June, a
storm blew up and destroyed the American
Mulberry Harbor at Omaha Beach.
126,000 GIs and 140,000 tons of material
could not be put ashore.
The logistical battle was now of prime
importance. Lack of men and armaments
meant that the Americans couldn't
advance through the Cotentin Peninsula
to capture Cherbourg as quickly as
planned.
To make matters worse, the British was
supposed to take Caen on the 7th of
June.
Two weeks after that date, General
Montgomery had to admit to a very angry
Eisenhower that he'd failed.
Allied strategists had underestimated
the importance of Normandy's bocage
landscape.
>> [music]
>> Every hedgerow was a death trap,
concealing snipers.
While the Atlantic Wall had not been
effective, the bocage was formidable.
The mobile war had become transformed
into a grueling positional war.
A handful of defenders was able to cause
enormous losses.
Samuel Fuller
>> With all the heaps of information the
intelligence services had gathered for
Overlord,
you would have thought they could have
told us about the strategic difficulty
of fighting the enemy in that horrible
tangle of hedgerows.
We didn't march into Normandy.
We were on our hands and knees.
>> The commandos thought they would get out
of this trap in a few days.
They were wrong.
One anonymous general confirmed,
>> "This damned war could go on for another
10 years."
>> At the end of the month of June 1944,
the Allies were still making no headway.
Rain was falling non-stop and caused 50%
of air missions to be canceled.
It was a time of great despondency.
The Americans were still trying to reach
Cherbourg.
Karl von Schlieben, a Hitler loyalist
who had fought on the Russian front,
held the fort with 21,000 men.
The Führer had ordered him to hold out
until the last bullet.
But the Germans didn't expect the
lightning attack launched by the
American General Collins, who was
nicknamed Lightning Joe.
His armored columns cut across the
Cotentin Peninsula and took the high
ground above Cherbourg.
>> The Germans didn't stand a chance,
but they obeyed orders and fought on.
Scattered throughout the town, their
snipers caused havoc.
The GIs had to fight from house to
house.
Greg Boyes
>> The town was dangerous.
We hugged the walls as we advanced.
No one spoke.
I thought, they are there, in that
house, or in the one opposite.
I would have given anything to be
somewhere else.
>> Cherbourg's commander, Karl von
Schlieben, as well as Robert Sattler,
commander of the naval dockyard, had
ordered their troops to defend the town
to the last drop of their blood.
They were the first to raise their
hands. [music]
They surrendered to General Collins.
Just a few months earlier, these senior
officers had been happily swimming in
the English Channel.
Whenever he lost a battle, Hitler laid
the blame on his generals. He ranted,
>> that loudmouth Schlieben was nothing but
a great coward.
>> The Allies took 40,000 prisoners, who
were not sorry their war was over.
The Americans had at last reached their
objective, except for one detail. The
Germans had sabotaged all military
installations.
It would be several weeks before this
deep water port could be used.
>> [bell]
>> The people of Cherbourg came out to
celebrate their liberation.
Paul Vassell recounts,
>> We hadn't heard the church bells ring
out for 4 years, and now this time it
was true. We were free.
>> The town's mayor, Paul Renault, gave
General Collins and his men a warm
welcome at the town hall.
General Collins tried his hand at
addressing the people in their own
language.
By the 1st of July 1944, there were a
million English and American soldiers in
Normandy.
Time was against the Germans.
They could do nothing to slow down the
non-stop flow of material pouring off
the ships.
Especially as the allies had a trump
card.
They controlled the skies.
German squadrons were conspicuously
absent.
To such an extent that a joke was
circulating in the Wehrmacht. If you see
a white plane, it's American. If you see
a black plane, it's English. If you
don't see anything,
it's the Luftwaffe.
The Fuhrer's generals were losing
patience.
The commander-in-chief, Marshal Keitel,
asked head of the Western Front von
Rundstedt, "What are we going to do?"
Von Rundstedt retorted, "Make peace,
idiot."
His insolence certainly led to his
dismissal.
The Fuhrer had sworn that Germany would
win whatever the cost.
And the troops shared his elation.
The young soldiers were not ready to lay
down their weapons.
The defense of the fatherland and the
hope of metals drove them on.
Hans Werk, a member of the Hitler Youth.
>> We'd been trained to fight to the death
for the fatherland, and that's what we
wanted to do.
>> Eisenhower was worried by such
fanaticism.
The hails of shells, the snipers
bullets, the atrocious weather, and
ever-present death caused an epidemic of
mental sickness to spread.
>> What's your trouble?
>> I can't stand seeing people killed.
>> Did you see people killed?
>> Lots of them.
>> What?
>> And what happened up there?
>> They got
the men on a hard slope.
Germans start shelling.
They were trapped.
Couldn't get out.
>> The illness disabled thousands of
soldiers, both English and American.
They were traumatized by all the
bloodshed they'd seen. Some were in such
a state of shock they could no longer
fight.
>> You're back on the battlefield now.
What are you doing? You're in your hole
now. What's happening?
>> The Germans rushed
our holes.
>> Yes, go on.
The shells are coming in. Where are you?
>> Uh I'm rolling out of my hole.
>> And what happens then?
>> I don't know
how the other body is laying there.
>> What do you do then?
>> I crawl and
follow him.
>> Some combatants thought [music] they
were still on the battlefield. At the
slightest noise, they threw themselves
to the floor to shelter from imaginary
shells.
Some of the generals opted for
strong-arm tactics, shooting the wimps
to make an example of them.
But the psychiatrists preferred treating
the sick, so they could send [music]
them back to their units.
The dream of a rapid victory was buried
in the bocage.
Faced with a stalemate at the front, the
allies increased the shelling of the
towns of Normandy.
Civilian populations lived through days
of terror.
Joseph Pottier
>> A swarm of incendiary bombs rained down
on the district. There were flames
everywhere, and the fire leaped from one
building to another near my house. It
was terrifying.
There were more than 20 separate fires.
>> Le Havre, Saint-Lô, Caen, Valognes, and
many other towns were treated as if they
were German towns, as enemies.
The death toll of the bombings was
devastating. 14,000 civilians perished
in Lower Normandy, more than the number
of soldiers killed on the evening of 6th
of June, and for only paltry gains.
A British soldier observed,
>> It was all more like a game of slaughter
than anything else.
It was as if, in order to liberate
people, you had to kill half of them and
destroy their houses and everything they
owned.
Funny method.
So many civilians decided to flee from
the devastated towns.
Just like in 1940, it was an exodus, but
this time people were running away from
the [music] allies.
Jacqueline Simon Corge, a French
officer, had the task of protecting
civilians.
>> Everything had been destroyed. The flow
of refugees was endless. We had to keep
setting up reception [music] centers.
We could never have imagined such a
situation.
>> The refugees lost everything.
Their houses,
families,
and sometimes their lives.
Vichy propaganda poured oil on the fire
by caricaturing the Allied help that was
supposing to be liberating France.
Radio London was represented by an
anti-Semitic cartoon.
The British and Americans are depicted
as Mickey Mouse and Donald Duck
destroying cities.
>> [laughter]
>> Despite the saturation bombing, the
British was still blocked outside the
town of Caen.
It was painfully obvious that Montgomery
was powerless.
The stalemate was heightening tension.
Eisenhower flew into a rage.
>> After dropping 7,000 tons of bombs on
advanced enemy positions, we've only
advanced 6 miles.
Can we afford 1,000 tons of bombs for
every mile?
>> The American generals railed against the
British who were leaving the GIs to
fight on alone.
The allies were at breaking point.
One month after the landings, only a
tiny part of the territory had been
liberated.
Nevertheless, the 14th of July was
celebrated in the number of towns in
Normandy.
In the small town of Isigny, free at
last from the Germans, the allies were
fated.
Louis Brereton, one of the heads of the
American Air Force, gave a speech in his
very best French.
>> About who?
>> [music]
[applause]
>> After the speeches and the hymns, it was
time for the handouts.
Major Hargreaves, a British Army doctor,
wrote to his wife,
"The poor children [music] all around us
are wildly excited at the sight of
chocolate and sweets.
The farmer's wife told me that her
children had gone [music] without sweets
for 3 years.
A lot of the children are pale and very
thin. I'm afraid that many [music] of
them are suffering from tuberculosis."
A member of the Resistance, Charles Le
Vaillant, recounted,
"It was the first 14th of July of
freedom. After all, we had the crowds on
our backs for 4 years. We felt [music]
liberated without the sound of boots in
our countryside. We were relieved. We
felt free and and especially free to
think what we wanted.
Five days later on the 19th of July
after a massive bombing raid, the town
of Caen was at last taken by the allies.
But it was more than 43 days after
D-Day.
The town was destroyed. 9,000 houses
were flattened. Only 1,000 were still
standing.
Sometimes refugees were cared for.
But generally, they were alone. They had
fled their villages.
They gave each other news as well they
could.
The radio became their lifeline.
>> The allies tried hard to bring in
supplies to care for people, to restore
phone lines.
But faced with such destruction,
bitterness sometimes broke through.
Jeanne Le Cornec, a 14-year-old girl
from Caen, took a British soldier to
task.
>> Why have you done this to us? Why were
all these civilians killed? Aren't we
your friends?
>> The soldier answered,
"We get ourselves killed for you, and
this is how you thank us?"
The two faces of war,
the joy of liberation,
the sorrow at such destruction.
Germany fought back.
Might she cave in?
Plenty of Allied soldiers hoped so in
their [music] prayers,
which sometimes seemed to be answered.
On the 20th of July, 1944, a German
officer, Claus von Stauffenberg, planted
a bomb in the Führer's headquarters.
Several men were seriously wounded.
But Hitler was spared.
When the Germans learned that their
leader had survived, they wept with joy.
"Thanks to God, the Führer has
survived." was heard in the streets of
Berlin.
German soldier Günther Volz wrote to his
wife,
>> "The news of the attempt to assassinate
the Führer came as a bombshell here.
It's a crime against the fatherland, a
real stab in the back."
>> Hitler was slightly injured and felt
that he had escaped by miracle. Just one
dressing blocked up his ear. He went to
visit victims of the attempted
assassination.
The allies hoped that the plot would
have weakened the regime.
But on the contrary, it merely served to
strengthen it.
Purge after purge followed.
Endued with a sort of mysticism, Hitler
confided,
>> "Clearly, nothing can happen to me.
My destiny is to follow my [music] path
and complete my task."
>> The British were still at a standstill.
Despite the capture of Caen,
reinforcements were building up in the
rear, but were having difficulty getting
to the front.
They had to advance, whatever the cost.
Especially as in the east a month
before, the Soviets had launched a vast
operation, Bagration.
More than 2 million men, 4,000 tanks,
25,000 cannons, and 6,000 planes were
advancing from Belarus.
If the Anglo-American army didn't break
through, the red flag would flutter over
a great part of Europe.
Aware of the danger, the American
General Bradley swung into action.
On the 25th of July, he launched
Operation Cobra.
Unable to break through to Caen in the
British sector, the offensive would take
place on the American side in the
Cotentin.
The aircraft of the US Air Force bombed
the enemy lines.
The Germans were pulverized by 4,000
tons of bombs.
The Americans poured into the breach.
They liberated Periers, Coutances, then
hurtled south towards Avranches.
The army could at last be deployed.
Stunned by the violence of the clash,
the Germans fled, leaving behind them
the dead and wounded.
German General Bayerlein recounted,
"The effect on our troops was
indescribable. Survivors went mad. They
became [music] good-for-nothing.
I do not believe hell could be worse
than what we went through."
But the Americans didn't use kid gloves.
Their carpet bombing also hit friendly
troops.
Over 600 of them were killed.
Among them was General Lesley McNair,
sent to the front as an observer.
A monumental blunder that the censors
tried to cover up.
It didn't work.
The war correspondents recounted the
drama, much to the annoyance of the
Allied leaders.
The American troops fanned out. A
smaller group headed for Brittany.
Another went east to surround the German
troops in the area south of Falaise, the
Falaise pocket.
It was an unexpected chance to wipe out
a large part of the German army.
The mission was assigned to the American
George Patton.
The general with the ivory handled Colts
and the chromed helmet was a headstrong
warrior known for his bad temper.
Commanding the third army, he galvanized
his troops.
>> I believe that an ounce of sweat will
save a gallon of blood. The harder we
push, the more Germans we kill.
The more Germans we kill, the fewer of
our men will be killed.
>> His third army raced to attack from the
south.
The English and Canadians attacked from
the north.
The Germans were trapped.
German soldier Fritz Mohr remembers,
>> We threw ourselves face down on the
ground.
I rested my head on the earth
as far as my helmets allowed.
My beautiful earth,
I thought, open up just a little
and take me into your bosom.
>> Thousands of German soldiers perished in
the hell that was the Falaise pocket.
Browbeaten by his commanders who asked
him to hang on at whatever cost, German
General Bayerlein answered,
>> "Rest assured, my men will not retreat 1
in because they are all dead."
>> But the victory was less spectacular
than expected. The Allies could have
completely surrounded the German army,
but once again Montgomery's troops
hadn't advanced quickly enough.
Despite the pincer movement, nearly
100,000 enemy soldiers managed to flee
from that hell.
It was 70 days since D-Day.
On Omaha Beach, the atmosphere had
changed.
The Allies logistical chain was now
running smoothly.
The Normandy lock was blown. The British
and Americans were pushing forward along
every French road to the immense
satisfaction of French General Leclerc,
who had landed in France with his second
armored division on the 1st of August.
He confided,
>> "I feel as if I'm reliving the situation
in 1940, but in reverse. The enemy in
total disarray, his columns taken
completely by surprise."
>> At the same time on the 15th of August,
a [music] Franco-American expeditionary
force landed in Provence.
The operation named Dragoon unfolded
much better than the one in Normandy.
The Allied forces under Generals Patch
and de Lattre [music] de Tassigny
advanced rapidly up the Rhone Valley.
In the face of such military
superiority, Hitler admitted defeat.
For the first time, he gave the order
for a general withdrawal,
leaving the way open for the Allied
armies.
>> [music]
>> The arrival of the Allies brought joy to
the liberated towns,
but sometimes violence broke out.
Collaborators, real or presumed, were
summarily executed.
Women accused of fraternizing with the
occupiers had their heads shaven and
were publicly humiliated on town
squares.
One woman recounted,
>> "They sat us on chairs with the hair
clippers.
As the hair fell, [music]
they applauded, laughed, and whistled.
We were terrorized.
I recognized some [music] who had been
with the Germans the day before, but now
they were wearing the FFI armband.
>> This spontaneous purging caused about
10,000 deaths.
The euphoria of liberation was not
enough to wipe out people's resentment.
[music]
Hatred ran rife in the summer of '44.
The summer of dances
and firing squads.
Even the liberators could descend into
violence.
While they were universally cheered, the
atrocious behavior of some of them
spoiled the party.
Some soldiers offended time and time
again, from simple theft to armed
robbery.
Others committed crimes, especially
rape.
For the British and Americans, France
was a land of milk and honey, the land
of wine, of love, and easy women.
Why not enjoy it all?
The land of Rabelais seemed like an
immense outlet for sex, where some of
the warriors claimed their due.
Such violence appalled the civilian
population.
An article in the Cherbourg press
sounded the alarm.
>> Scenes of savagery and bestiality
despoil our countryside. Men are
pillaging, raping, murdering. All
security has disappeared in our homes as
well as on our roads. Real acts of
terror are spreading panic.
>> Before long, a grim joke was going
around the Normandy population.
>> Under the Germans, our men had to hide
themselves.
With the Americans,
we have to hide our women.
>> Officers repressed these awful crimes
and immediately punished the guilty
before they discredited the whole army.
The British and Americans pushed on at
last towards the east. The Normandy
campaign was over. The Battle of Paris
was just beginning.
In the capital, the atmosphere was
electric. Parisians were awaiting their
liberation.
Hitler ordered the military governor of
Paris, General von Choltitz, to put down
any attempt to revolt.
20,000 heavily armed Germans were tasked
with defending the capital and were even
told to destroy it if the Führer so
ordered.
In spite of this grave threat, [music]
the police came out on strike and seized
the police headquarters on the 19th of
August
and then defended it against German
assaults.
In a stroke of cruel irony, the men who
had rounded up the Jews were manning the
front line alongside the resistance.
Inspector Roger Belbeoch of the
Communist resistance
was amused.
>> In the courtyard of the police
headquarters, a miracle happened.
Everyone was a resistant. It was quite
simple. Every policeman [music] was a
resistant. All you had to do was tear a
picture of Marshal Pétain to shreds and
walk around with an FFI armband.
>> A popular uprising broke out led by the
head of the FFI of the Paris region, the
Communist Henri Rol-Tanguy. His
watchword was "Everyone get his own
crowd."
Parisian woman Hélène Cance said,
>> "The battle began between the two sides,
the FFI on our left and Germans on our
right. It raged for three full hours in
the street.
My mom locked me in the house. We closed
the shutters because of the bullets
flying around.
>> As Paris rose up, de Gaulle, back in
France, met Eisenhower on the 20th of
August.
The capital was not among the Americans'
objectives,
but de Gaulle was adamant that Paris
should not suffer the same fate as
Warsaw. It was essential to support the
insurgents and avoid a bloodbath.
De Gaulle also wanted to prevent the
FFI, led by the communists, taking
power. He intended to restore the
Republic and place himself at its head.
Eisenhower did not see things in the
same light.
De Gaulle argued,
>> "The fate of Paris is of paramount
interest to the French government. For
this reason, I find that I must
intervene and insist you send in
troops."
>> Eisenhower finally agreed.
>> [music]
>> General Leclerc's 2nd Armored Division
was the first to rush to the aid of the
Parisians,
but at the request of the Pentagon,
black soldiers were transferred from
this unit even before it was created.
Washington did not wish them to march
proudly down the Champs-Élysées.
Although this war was being waged in the
name of liberty, racism had still not
disappeared from the US Army's ranks.
>> While Paris descended into turmoil,
Hitler ordered von Choltitz to reduce
the city to rubble. The Grand Palais was
already ablaze.
The streets were full of barricades to
hinder the movement of German troops.
Parisians resisted, but they had
precious few weapons and could not fight
on for long.
On the 25th of August, Leclerc's
division entered the city
just in time.
After 4 years of darkness, Paris was
going to be free at last.
Both the people and their liberators
dissolved into tears.
Edgar Morin, a young resistant,
Leclerc's tanks arrived, exhausted men
with tears in their eyes as we ourselves
were weeping. We were living a sublime
moment of happiness that will remain in
my memory as one of the most beautiful
moments of my life.
With the arrival of the allies and the
rebellion of the population,
the Germans capitulated.
Terror had changed sides.
A German soldier recalled,
"We set out on the most humiliating
march of our lives.
We were bombarded with insults.
The strong crowded round us yelling,
'Hang the murderers, gang of murderers
and thieves. Death to the Krauts.'
We were beaten, pushed, and shoved, spat
on. Wild animals had been set [music] on
us.
>> In the afternoon of the 25th of August,
General de Gaulle went to the Paris Town
Hall.
He was resentful and spoke not one word
of thanks to the allies who had wanted
to keep him from power.
>> [music]
>> The next day, the 26th of August, the
whole population gathered on the
Champs-Élysées.
2 million Parisians cheered de Gaulle
and celebrated the long-awaited
liberation.
Captain Dronne of the 2nd AD wrote,
"A human wave flooded the most [music]
beautiful avenue in the world. General
de Gaulle was there. For him, it was a
consecration. It showed that he had the
direct support of the people that he so
sorely wanted and desired.
From that moment on, how could anyone
pretend that he did not legitimately
represent France.
The liberation of Paris by the revolt of
its people has become a part of history
forever.
It is seen as a prelude to the
subsequent fall of the Reich.
The allies were not thanked by de
Gaulle, but the people of Paris took
care of that.
>> Hello, baby. [music]
Mademoiselle. Hello, baby. [singing]
Mademoiselle. Run that with me,
Mademoiselle. I have to return to my
company.
You're good for me,
Mademoiselle. Me good for you,
Mademoiselle.
>> [screaming]
>> But the enthusiasm generated by these
memorable days soon faded.
Robert Capa was there.
>> The day Paris was liberated was the most
unforgettable ever. And 7 days later
came the most miserable [music] day.
There was nothing left to eat, nothing
to drink. The girls had all gone back
home to recount what they'd seen.
The shops were shut, the streets were
empty, and suddenly we realized that the
war wasn't over.
It was raging on less than 20 miles
away.
>> Indeed, the fight had to go on.
In mid-September, the armies coming from
Normandy and the expeditionary force
that had landed in Provence at last
joined forces.
>> It had taken nearly 100 days to liberate
the greater part of the country.
>> The challenge of Overlord had been won.
But the war was not over.
It would take another eight months to be
finally done with the Third Reich.
Over 117,000
soldiers killed between June and August
1944 have their resting place in
Normandy.
Such a heavy price to pay.
The Battle of Normandy was decisive in
the liberation of France.
Old stones, graves, ruined bunkers
remind us of those days of tears and
glory that helped us to conquer that
[music] brown plague and taste once more
the intoxication of freedom.
May all liberated people swear
they will never forget.
>> [music]
>> Hallelujah.